<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>A proclamation made by the States of the vnited Netherlands touching the defence of the safegard of the enemy, the breaking of the quarters with the enemies souldiours, which vndertake to come ouer the waters and bogs in the parts of Freesland, Ornlanden, Drente, and Westerwoldingerland, or Lordship of Wedde. Faithfully translated out of Dutch. Also a copie of a letter, to the honourable Lords, the States, bearing date the 21 of March, 1599. Touching the victorie atchieued by the Prince Maurites before Emmericke.</title>
            <author>United Provinces of the Netherlands. Staten Generaal.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1599</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 10 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 7 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2011-04">2011-04 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A08088</idno>
            <idno type="STC">STC 18453</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC S109950</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99845580</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99845580</idno>
            <idno type="VID">10487</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A08088)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 10487)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1475-1640 ; 736:17)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>A proclamation made by the States of the vnited Netherlands touching the defence of the safegard of the enemy, the breaking of the quarters with the enemies souldiours, which vndertake to come ouer the waters and bogs in the parts of Freesland, Ornlanden, Drente, and Westerwoldingerland, or Lordship of Wedde. Faithfully translated out of Dutch. Also a copie of a letter, to the honourable Lords, the States, bearing date the 21 of March, 1599. Touching the victorie atchieued by the Prince Maurites before Emmericke.</title>
                  <author>United Provinces of the Netherlands. Staten Generaal.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[16] p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>By [J. Windet for] Iohn Wolfe, and are to be sold at his shop in Popes head Alley, neere to the Exchange,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>Imprinted at London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1599.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Actual printer's name from STC.</note>
                  <note>In two parts; the second part has a separate title page, with same imprint, reading: The copie of a letter written to the honorable Lords, the States, bearing date the 21 of March, 1599. Touching a victory atchieued by the Prince Maurits before Emmericke. Translated out of the copie, printed at Amsterdam.</note>
                  <note>Part 2 title page bound out of order, behind general title page.</note>
                  <note>Signatures: A-B⁴.</note>
                  <note>Some print show-through.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of the original in the British Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Netherlands --  History --  Wars of Independence, 1566-1648 --  Sources.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2009-12</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2009-12</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-02</date>
            <label>Mona Logarbo</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-02</date>
            <label>Mona Logarbo</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-04</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:10487:1"/>
            <!-- PDF PAGE 8 -->
            <pb facs="tcp:10487:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <!-- PDF PAGE 8 -->
            <p>A PROCLAMATION made by the States of the vnited Netherlands, touching the defence of the ſafe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gard of the enemy, the breaking of the quarters with the enemies ſouldiours, which vndertake to come ouer the wa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters and bogs in the parts of Freeſland, Omlanden, Drente, and Weſterwoldingerland, or Lordſhip of Wedde.</p>
            <p>Faithfully tranſlated out of Dutch.</p>
            <p>Alſo a Copie of a Letter, to the honourable Lords, the States, bearing date the 21 of March, 1599. Touching the victorie atchieued by the Prince <hi>Maurits</hi> before Emmericke.</p>
            <figure>
               <head>I W</head>
               <figDesc>printer's or publisher's device</figDesc>
            </figure>
            <p>Imprinted at London by Iohn Wolfe, and are to be ſold at his ſhop in Popes head Alley, neere to the Exchange. 1599.</p>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="letter">
            <pb facs="tcp:10487:2"/>
            <!-- PDF PAGE 9 -->
            <pb facs="tcp:10487:2"/>
            <!-- PDF PAGE 9 -->
            <head>The Copie of a Letter.</head>
            <head type="sub">To the honorable Lords, the States, dated the 21 of March, 1599. touching victorie atchieued by the Prince <hi>Maurits before Emmericke.</hi>
            </head>
            <opener>
               <salute>
                  <seg rend="decorInit">M</seg>Oſt honourable Lords,</salute>
            </opener>
            <p>his princely excelencie writeth from Arnham the 19 of this preſent month, to haue viſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted all the bordring citties, and haue fortified the ſame: To haue had intelligence, that the Cardinall being come towards Gelder, the Admirant vvas trauailed to meet him. That his princely excellency had found good to ſurpriſe the caſtle of Zeuenter, vvith two houſen. That the princes ſouldiors in Zeuenter not vvith<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out great difficulty, after three vollies of demy-cannons had yeelded vp the fort. That the Counte <hi>Lodowicke</hi> vvas mean vvhile ſent
<pb facs="tcp:10487:3"/>
               <!-- PDF PAGE 10 -->vvith the horſemen neere Emmerick, as ſup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſing that the gariſons vvould come out to aſsiſt the aforeſaid places, as indeed it happe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned: for they perceiuing ſome of our horſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>men hold a great pace, as if they had ſhun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned the citty. The Earle of Buſquoy, Gouer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nour of Emmericke (vvhoſe vvife amongſt others vvent to Spaine vvith the Archduke <hi>Albertus</hi> to fetch the Infanta) vvith a great troupe of the gariſon, came out of the citty to purſue our horſmen, vvhich they did a great vvay beyond the ambuſh, inſomuch, that be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing incloſed, the ſaid Earle and two captains vvith many officers vvere taken, and very neer a hundreth drowned. Alſo thirty ſouldiours vvere ſet at liberty, for the vvhich the Earle hath promiſed ranſome, his perſon is vvoun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded, but (according to his excellencies vvri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting) not mortally: declareth, that the enemy maketh daily great preparation to come into the field. God be praiſed for this good beginning.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="proclamation_of_the_states_of_the_Netherlands">
            <pb facs="tcp:10487:3"/>
            <!-- PDF PAGE 10 -->
            <head>
               <g ref="char:leaf">❧</g> A Proclamation made by the States of the vnited Nether-lands, touching the defence of the ſafegard of the enemie, the brea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>king of the quarters with the enemies ſouldiours, who vndertake to come ouer the waters and bogs in the parts of Freeſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land, Omlanden, Drenthe, and Weſterwoldin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gerland, or Lordſhip of Wedde.</head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">T</seg>He generall States of the vnited Nether-lands, to all thoſe vvhich ſhall ſee or heare theſe preſent gree<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting. Whereas vvee are in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>formed, that the enemie vvith a neuer-heard barbarous preſumption, deceit and vvickedneſſe (as if all vvhat he liſt to doe vvere lawfull) againſt all diuine, natu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rall, and humane lawes, againſt all faith, ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nor, oath, and beleefe, hauing moſt lamenta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bly and cruelly oppreſſed, pilled, and infuſed the feeble, vnarmed, and guiltleſſe, neutrall
<pb facs="tcp:10487:4"/>
               <!-- PDF PAGE 11 -->cities and townes, yea of his beſt and vvell-vvillingeſt friends, and finally are ranged to the borders of theſe vnited Prouinces, vvhere although he vvas by the means of our might, and armes, through the wiſe and valiant con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>duct of his excellencie, next God, repulſed, and diſapointed of his enterpriſe, yet ceaſeth not by letters, meſſages, threats, and other<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vvaies, to procure diuers of our countries and inhabitants of theſe vnited Prouinces, as Freeſeland, Omlanden, Drente, Oldampt, Weſtervvoldingerland, or Lordſhip of Wedde, to come vnder his contribution, vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der colour of his ſafegard, as if hee (vvho in ſuch faithleſſe, vvicked, and cruel ſort had be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>haued himſelfe towards theſe poore good neutrals, yea his owne friends) vvould behaue himſelfe faithfully and meekely towards our inhabitants his enemies. And being that vve are vvell aſſured, that hee intendeth nothing els, then that hauing by theſe his adulations allured and enticed by little and little our good inhabitants to his deuotion, in the end vvith all crueltie and tirannie to handle them, and therefore thinke it moſt expedient, by all poſsible meanes to preuent it. So it is, that
<pb facs="tcp:10487:4"/>
               <!-- PDF PAGE 11 -->by deliberation of the counſell of eſtate of the aforeſaid vnited lands, vve haue interdi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cted and defended expreſſely by theſe pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſents, on paine of our higheſt diſgrace and diſpleaſure to be held as enemies, and vvith<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out anie fauour to be immediately puniſhed. All townes, villages, places, and quarters of Freeſeland, Omlanden, Drente, Oldampt, and Weſtervvoldingerland, together vvith the Officers, Magiſtrates, and inhabitants of the ſame, high and low, noble and ignoble, as vvell in generall as perticular, in any man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner vvhatſoeuer not to take or receiue of the enemie anie ſafegard, or vnder pretext of the ſame to yeeld, accord, or pay the enemie any contribution, great or ſmall, or to harbour or hide anie of the enemies ſouldiours, or to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceiue any meſſage by mouth or letters of the enemie, and much leſſe to hold any correſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pondence by mouth or vvritings vvith him. But to the contrarie, ordaine, vvill, and com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mand expreſſely all the aforeſaid townes, vil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lages, places, quarters, and inhabitants, vvith<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out delay to furniſh and prepare themſelues vpon the needful places to keep good watch, and by all needfull and due order, either by
<pb facs="tcp:10487:5"/>
               <!-- PDF PAGE 12 -->
               <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
                  <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
               </gap>
               <pb facs="tcp:10487:5"/>
               <!-- PDF PAGE 12 -->
               <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
                  <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
               </gap>
               <pb facs="tcp:10487:6"/>
               <!-- PDF PAGE 13 -->ſound of bels, hornes, or beacons, to aſſem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble themſelues; and iointly to vvithſtand, purſue, and kill, or at leaſt, take priſoners all ſuch foe-like ſouldiours, as ſhall preſume, or dare to come ouer the vvaters and bogs in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to theſe territories. To vvhich end vvee like<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vviſe declare, ordaine, and command, that henceforward no quarter ſhall be held with ſuch enemies or foe-like ſouldiours: Which keeping of quarter vve haue for that cauſe al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>together and vvholly depoſed and renoun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ced, as by theſe preſents vve yet depoſe and renounce the ſame. Vpon paine, that vvhoſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>euer henceforward ſhall bee found to haue kept quarter vvith the ſaid foe-like ſouldiors, or to haue in any ſort ſhewed them any fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uour or kindneſſe, that thoſe ſhall at the in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtant be ſtaied, and immediately vvithout any fauour puniſhed as the foe-like ſouldiors themſelues. And to the end, that euerie one may acquit himſelfe vvith more courage and zeale towards his enemie, vve haue agreed, and agree by the preſents, for an honour and recompence to euerie one, bee hee ſouldi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>our or no ſouldiour, the ſumme of fiſt y<note n="*" place="margin">100 ſhil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lings of En<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gliſh mony.</note> gul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dens for euerie foe-like ſouldior, vvhich by
<pb facs="tcp:10487:6"/>
               <!-- PDF PAGE 13 -->anie henceforward ſhal be killed (vpon good proofes) or at leaſtwiſe taken priſoner. As al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſo in like manner vve agree and promiſe the ſumme of fiue and twentie<note n="*" place="margin">Fifty ſhil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lings En<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gliſh mony.</note> guldens, to each and euerie one vvhoſoeuer, that ſhall ſurelie, trulie, and vvithout fraud accuſe anie one to the contrarie of our expreſſe commaunde<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments, vvhich ſhall haue receiued anie ſafe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gard, paied anie contribution, to haue harbo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red or hid anie of the aforeſaid ſouldiours, to haue by mouth or by vvriting held anie cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reſpondence vvith the enemie, or that hauing taken anie enemie, ſhall haue vvithout, or vpon ranſome, let him go. And to the end, that none may pretend ignorance of theſe our expreſſe ordinances, We deſire our belo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ued States of Freeſla<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>d, the city of Groningen, and Omlanden, or their deputies, and all others to vvhom it doth belong and apper<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taine, immediatly to cauſe proclamation and publication hereof to be made in euery and each citty, place, and quarter, vvhere it ſhall be needfull. As alſo earneſtly requeſting the noble Lord, the Earle <hi>William Lodowicke</hi> of Naſſau, gouernour of Freeſeland, the citty of Groningen &amp; Omlanden, &amp;c. vvill &amp; com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mand
<pb facs="tcp:10487:7"/>
               <!-- PDF PAGE 14 -->expreſſely all cheefetaines, knights, captaines, commanders, and common ſoul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diours, horſe and foot, by vvater and land, al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſo all officers, iuſtices, and inhabitants, vnto vvhom this in any ſort may touch or belong, to gouerne themſelues according to the te<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nour hereof, and inuiolably to accompliſh and keep the contents of the ſame, vpon pain of the paines aboue named, for that vve haue found the ſame to bee moſt expedient and neceſſarie for the good of the Land.</p>
            <closer>
               <dateline>Giuen in S Grauen Haeghe, <date>the twentith of March. 1599.</date>
               </dateline>
               <signed>Fr. Duyck. V.</signed>
            </closer>
            <postscript>
               <p>By the commandement of the Lords, the generall States of the vnited Netherlands.</p>
               <p>And by the counſell of eſtate of the ſame.</p>
               <closer>
                  <signed>Chriſtopher Huygens.</signed>
               </closer>
            </postscript>
         </div>
         <div type="postscript">
            <pb facs="tcp:10487:7"/>
            <!-- PDF PAGE 14 -->
            <opener>
               <dateline>
                  <date>From the Haghe, the 21 of March, 1599.</date>
               </dateline>
            </opener>
            <p>Thoſe of Arnhem haue ſince reported, that aboue 150, which in the skirmiſh thinking to ſaue themſelues through the water, were drow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned, and that amongſt them were ſome with gold chaines. Thoſe of Emmericke repent themſelues alreadie to haue with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out any need taken the Spani<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ards in, which was againſt their promiſe.</p>
         </div>
         <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
